Arbitrage opportunities are now like always available.
And so the funds that we were using to deploy into the arbitrage box were idle for some time.
So we were like, okay, we need to find a way to make that more efficient.
In 2022, we realized that most of the customer base for idle finance was
to be shown funds are locating across different strategies.
And one of the major feedback that we received at that time was that
your doctor optimization is great, but we need to take care of risk and risk diversification.
So at that time, we decided to introduce some yield of tranches.
Credit lines can be really customized from underwriting terms, covenants, to compliance requirements.
This is something that, like for example, maple or centrifuge is a bit limited, I would say.
The credit lines that we have are creation-based.
So we are not the only one that are underwriting these kind of credit lines,
but we opened up these processes also to third-party curators.
Welcome to Epicenter, the show which talks about the technologies, projects,
and people driving decentralization and the blockchain revolution.
I'm Frederica Anst, and today I'm speaking with Mateo Pandolfi, who is the co-founder of Pareto,
a credit coordination protocol that evolved out of idle Dow
in Anders' building on-chain markets for private credit.
Before I talk with Mateo, let me tell you about our sponsors this week.
If you're looking to stake your crypto with confidence, look no further than Chorus 1.
More than 150,000 delegators, including institutions like BitGo,
Pantera Capital, and Ledger, trust Chorus 1 with their assets.
They support over 50 blockchains and are leaders in governance on networks like Cosmos ensuring your stake
is responsibly managed.
Thanks to their advanced MEV research, you can also enjoy the highest-taking rewards.
You can stake directly from your preferred wallet, set up a white label note,
restake your assets on eigenneo or symbiotic, or use the SDK for multi-chain saking in your app.
Learn more at Chorus.1 and start staking today.
Hey guys, I want to tell you about Gnosis, a collective of builders creating real tools for real people on the open internet.
Gnosis has been around since 2015.
In fact, it started as one of Ethereum's very first projects.
And today, it's grown into a whole ecosystem designed to make open finance actually work for everyday people.
At the center of it all is Gnosis Chain.
It's a low-cost, highly decentralized layer one that's compatible with Ethereum and secured by over 300,000 validators.
So whether you're building a DAP, experimenting with EFI, or working on autonomous agents,
Gnosis Chain gives you a solid, neutral foundation to build on.
But Gnosis is more than just infrastructure.
It's also tools that people can actually use.
Like circles, for example, let's anyone issue their own digital currency through networks of trust, not banks.
And then there's Metri.
It's their smart contract wallet that makes it easy to access circles, manage group currencies,
and even spend anywhere Visa has accepted thanks to their integration with Gnosis Pay.
All this is governed by Gnosis Dow, where anyone can propose, vote, and help guide the network.
And if you want to get involved, running a validator is super easy.
All you need is one GNO and some basic hardware.
To learn more and start building on the open internet, head to Gnosis.io.
Gnosis, building the open internet, one block at a time.
Mateo, it's super nice to have you on.
Really excited to be here, and yep, thanks to the entire epicenter team for hosting this session to all of you for tuning in as well.
Mateo, tell us a little bit about yourself before we dive into Pareto.
What's your professional and academic background?
Yeah, so before founding Pareto, and as we are going to go through more into details, I do Dow back in the past.
So my background is in finance.
So my academic career was pretty much in finance and entrepreneurship.
So it's kind of like a good mix that brought me into DeFi, this kind of like, you know, innovative market, but still really related to finance.
Before actually starting with Pareto and I do Dow, I was working on financial risk analysis.
So I was consulting with major financial institution in Italy, like it is some power, for example, on their credit desk.
So essentially do helping on the writing process and due diligence process in order to create this kind of like corporate bonds instrument for these financial institutions.
What drew you into the blockchain space in the first place?
That's a really good casting, because I've been brought into the DeFi space by my other co-founder, our CTO.
And who made me find out about Ethereum at first?
At that time, I was actually still a finance student, and we were exploring Ethereum.
We had a background in computer science, and with my background in finance, we were thinking how we could build something on Ethereum.
And the first instance of something that would build on-chain was actually touching the arbitrage and arbitrage bonds.
So, you know, what we know right now as MED, at that time was still called PGA price gas auction, you know.
So we started building these kind of bonds that were looking at discrepancies between taxes and taxes and arbitrage in price across these assets.
And yeah, so that was kind of like the first instance and the first way where I realized that we could really create something that was completely programmable and automatic,
and was really like changing the way that I was used to see finance.
Because, you know, from the academic, but even from the professional background, I always saw finance being quite sealed.
So, all these kind of closed systems that were all like communicating internally and not to each other.
And with Ethereum, that was like the first time that it was my ha-ha moment.
It is like, okay, that's really composable and that's something that we can build out to mission that runs on-chain and runs 24/7.
So, that was the first time I really touched with my hands, Ethereum and the power of smart contracts.
And then, you know, I just got into the rabbit hole of that.
So, we started exploring land in protocols, that's how it wasn't even a hobby. It was only compound and the YDX.
And so, then everything evolved into what brought us into idle finance and then those are later on.
When did you decide to kind of discontinue the arbitrage bot?
That's a good point because idle finance came out from a need that we had for the arbitrage bots.
Because actually, you know, arbitrage opportunities are now, like, always available.
And so, the funds that we were using to deploy into the arbitrage bots were idle for some time.
So, we were like, okay, we need to find a way to make that more efficient.
And so, I would say that we proposed idle finance as a way to optimize the yield on idle funds
in 2019 on an Akatonor on Gitcoin.
So, I think that was in 2019 when we decided to focus completely on an idle finance and put aside the arbitrage bots.
So, I would say 2019, we started the arbitrage bots back in 2017-2018.
So, yeah, we ran that for a couple of years and then decided to focus completely on idle finance.
And what's the rationale for kind of moving over purely a return on investment kind of play or what were the drivers here?
Scalability. One of the major drivers was scalability because with the arbitrage bots, we saw that by increasing the AUM,
the TVL of the arbitrage bots, we were actually reducing the margin of the funds for the arbitrage opportunities.
So, we were really focused on building something on Ethereum that could be scalable, you know.
So, when we started implementing the very first version of idle finance into our arbitrage bots,
we realized that we could manage 1 million to 100 million and the result was pretty much the same
in terms of return of the capital because the kind of optimization could be applied
with more capital compared to arbitrage bots.
So, building something that was able to be scalable and to be offered also to a more broader audience,
I would say, because, you know, arbitrage in general is quite a niche product or in general,
it's a niche concept that not a lot of users grasp or understand in general.
Instead, like automating the yield generation optimization yield generation across different
protocols was really something that was clicking with DeFi users at the time.
So, I would say, yeah, scalability and also being able to offer this kind of product
to a broader audience and let them understand the product to a broader audience was the main driver
of us focusing completely on idle finance.
There were quite a few projects that kind of centered around that, right?
Kind of, I mean, in the very beginning, it was things like incident that kind of let you kind of
switch funds between make and other memories correctly and then kind of more sophisticated
things like come along. So, how did idle Dow kind of fit into that landscape?
So, I think we had the lucky and the opportunity.
We have been lucky and we had the opportunity also to meet like,
instead of team or even Andrei Kranger from Bayern, even before like them building out their products.
I would say, instead of being really great that they have been really great builders
and but never really focused on yield optimization and automation of that yield optimization.
They were more focused on providing great tools for borrowers that were using like,
for example, compound, AAVE, or even maker Dow.
And I would say that instead of falls more into a different category compared to idle finance.
Why earn an idle finance are pretty much similar. Actually, I remember a lot of
conversation in Telegram with Andrei Kranger at the beginning on how to solve some like initial
issues of yield optimization like there was this ping-pong effect that we found out at the time
that was affecting yield aggregators, which means that essentially, when you move a big chunk of
the funds into a specific lending protocol, you also influence the interest rate on that specific
protocol. So, if you don't have control on the funds and control on the influence that you have
on the interest rate, you might end up into a ping-pong effect, which means that you move
all the funds from protocol A to protocol B because protocol B has the higher interest rate.
But when you do that, you're lowering the interest rate of protocol B and might become
lower than the protocol A. So, the yield aggregator sees that the higher interest rate is again on
protocol A. And so, you move back the funds from protocol A. So, you see that you create this
kind of ping-pong effect between by moving a rebalancing funds. So, we have been like
talking a lot and understanding what was the right, you know, algorithm and optimization mechanism
to take all these. Also, we have hundreds of cards at the beginning. And then I think
why you're indeed a great job on, I would say, the positioning and narrative built around the
yield aggregation. At the time, we were quite, you know, for starting Idaho Finance, as I mentioned,
we started with Gitcoin Acciton. So, we won that Gitcoin Acciton and then we got accepted into an
accelerator in New York with consensus. And so, we kind of took a more professional approach,
I would say, or institutional approach to the product. Instead, I think at the very early phase
of wire and they took more a digital approach, which turned out to be the right narrative. So,
I would like say that they did a great job on that side of things. And, of course, then the
dev team and the community that formed around wire was really great. So, congrats, of course,
on wire and Andrei Cronzo. I'm bootstrapping these at the beginning. And I would say that
we kind of, at the end of the day, DeFi was a small market at the beginning. So, the way that
we were looking at competitors at the beginning was more like co-petition, radar, that pure
competition. And so, it turned out that, like, one of the major partners for idle finance was
wire in itself. Like, with some of these strategies and the volts that wire had at the beginning,
like for USDC, USDT, and I, were based on idle finance yield optimization for a big chunk of the
funds that they were managing. So, it turned out to be kind of like a more a partnership
radar than a competition with wire in finance, for example. Of course, over time, DeFi market
evolved, become more sectoralized, more, you know, professionalized, and of course, competition
came out. But I would say that early times of DeFi, I really enjoyed the early times in DeFi
because it was all about, like, cooperating together and trying to build, like, you know,
all the legal pieces that you could put together in DeFi was really about this sentiment, was really
about this philosophical, you know, work together to grow the market instead of competing together
to shrink the market to each other. What ultimately kind of drove the pivot from idle to prattle?
I would say that we've focused a lot in for on yield optimization from since 2019 to, I would say,
2022. In 2022, we realized that most of the customer base for idle finance was
institutional funds. So, institutional funds are locating across different strategies.
And one of the major feedback that we received there at that time was that
yield optimization is great, but we need to take care of risk and risk diversification.
We need to mitigate risk for the liquidity providers. So, at that time, we decided to
introduce an additional product line and an additional primitive to the product suite,
which was yield the trenches. So, essentially, a primitive where we could
yield the senior and unit trenches, senior meds and unit trenches on top of potentially any DeFi
yield source. And so, these those are response to these kind of feedback that we received there.
And the continued and junior trenches in this context kind of being different rates of return
for different levels of risk. Do you mean something else by that? No, no, that's correct. That's correct.
Essentially, senior tranche is the most protected vehicle investment world that is protected by
the unit tranche. So, whatever there is default because of an actor or a loss of funds by the
borrowers or these kind of loss of funds, the unioners are first loss observation layer.
So, they absorb the loss on the alpha of the senior because of this risk that they bear,
they receive also an higher yield compared to the senior trenches. So, we introduced this primitive,
we started building around different kind of yield sources in DeFi over collateralized landings,
taking in order to understand also where was the product market fit for this kind of product line.
And we realized that most of the product market fit was on institution credit. At that time,
we were working with protocols like maple or clear pool that were doing these kind of first
instances of institutional credit on chain. And we saw that like liquidity providers and lenders
were really appreciating senior and unit tranches for institutional credit lines because
different credit funds, different badge funds or families offices had different views on these
specific institutional borrowers that they were lending to. And so, using senior or unit tranches
allowed them to customize the risk reward profile of their entire credit exposure of their entire
credit portfolio. So, we realized that most of the product market fit was there, but we received
also a lot of feedback from both borrowers and lenders that the credit infrastructure was not
ready for institutional needs. It was really kind of like mimicking a compound and have an
interest rate model, which was a paying for the borrower because it was a single borrower that
wanted to, with a variable interest rate, that operation on speaking was terrible because they
were looking more at the interest rate that they were paying compared to doing their own business.
And in general, the terms and the underwriting process for these kind of institutional credit
lines on chain at that time wasn't really customizable and modular, I would say.
And so, we realized most of the product market fit was there. There was room for improvements
on the credit space. So, we said, okay, we need to, we have a clear opportunity over there,
and we wanted to build and improve that space, that part of the DeFi sector, let's say.
So, that's pretty much how we transitioned to Pareto. We started working a lot with
institutional credit lines, and then we realized that we wanted to improve the credit lines themselves.
And that's how essentially Pareto came out.
Tell me more about the institutional borrowers. So, what kind of institutions were they that they
were willing to borrow in this very competitive market on chain, where you can go to your local
bank and probably get a more competitive loan? That's a good point because, of course, they could
access, you know, could originate on credit lines from a traditional bank, but the process of
origination takes a lot of time, especially the kind of borrowers that we're working with right
now are pretty much institutional funds that run delta neutral strategies or market makers or prime
brokerages. And the process of originating a loan and managing that loan in a traditional way
usually takes a lot of time and resources from their team. And usually the teams are now like
really huge, and so the overhead is really tangible for the final borrower. We recently actually run
a use case with one of our major borrowers, which is Falcon X, one of the leading market
and prime brokerages. And what came out of the use case is that before using on-chain credit lines,
so relying on traditional credit lines took around 80 hours per month from their team to make sure that
in order to originate, all the documentation was there, making sure that all the lenders were aware
of updated terms and also doing manual reconciliation. What came out of this is that now with the on-chain
credit line, they have to dedicate two hours per month, the same team. So operationally speaking,
the improvement for the borrower is really tangible. There is a streamlining process that is happening
on the operational side of things. On-chain credit lines are pretty much self-operating
compared to our traditional credit lines. So that's I would say the main advantage of operating
an on-chain credit line. And secondarily, I would say also being able to have a credit position that
is composable is a big advantage for these kind of borrowers. And a big advantage, I would say,
also for the lenders at the end of the day, because being able to use a credit position as a collateral
in a more for Euler, for example, or create an interest rate swap instrument using PENDO for the
same credit position, it's really powerful for the lenders. So lenders have a better, let's say, UX
when lending to this kind of institution. And interns borrowers are able to originate more
liquidity with these kind of credit lines and streamlining the process of managing these kind
of credit lines. Cool. There's a couple of projects kind of doing very similar things in the space,
so kind of the likes of Maple and Centrofuge and so on. So how is your approach different or is it
different from your competitors? So it is different. I think Centrofuge,
they started like really early, so they did a great job at pioneering on that on this kind of area.
And also Maple, they kind of pivoted, I remember back in, maybe it was 2020, 2021, and then they
focused completely on on chain credit. So both are doing great jobs on expanding this kind of space.
The main difference that we wanted to implement since the beginning of Orator was to make sure
that we have a highly customizable protocol. So credit lines can be really customized from
underwriting terms, covenants, to compliance requirements. And this is something that like,
for example, Maple or Centrofuge is a bit limited, I would say, but also more importantly,
the credit lines that we have are creation based. So we are not the only one that are underwriting
this kind of credit lines, but we opened up these processes also to third party curators.
It's kind of if you look at what happened with Marfo and other over collateralized lending
protocol in the past, where they introduced this kind of curation role, that's essentially the
saying that we're doing with Orator compared to other on chain credit products. These allows us
to have, again, more scalability for these kind of products, because we're not the only one on
the writing new borrowers, but we have other curators that can provide these kind of underwriting
capabilities. And also in our longer term vision, the the curation based model allows us to work
also with kind of like traditional financial institution. Instead, we see more like products
like Maple or Centrofuge kind of a in house underwriting company. So that's pretty much
like the main difference that we have. It's an open curation based model versus all in hours
underwriting process. So underwriting is actually really skill task, right? So kind of like what it
kind of takes is kind of you need to understand the books of this company, you need to understand
the business prospects, you need to kind of you need to calculate the default risk and the associated
interests you need to charge in order to kind of break even. Tell me how this process is handled
within Pareto and kind of like how you outsource this to others. So with Pareto, that's a really
good point in the sense that on the writing is, it requires a lot of skills and also a lot of
domain expertise, I would say. That's why also we started with institutional digital native funds.
So we are which are most familiar with what we have been doing in the past. So we completely
understand the kind of deployment and strategies that they're going to apply to the credit lines
that they're opening. And of course, like the first step, it's pretty much like, as you mentioned,
a scan and review of the creditworthiness of the borrower, which is given by analyzing the books
and the balance sheets of these kind of borrowers, making sure there is enough equity, for example,
to be able to cover for any losses to be. And I would say that like there's been some experimenting
underwriting in the past. I'm not talking about Pareto, but in the past, there's been
some experimenting underwriting small companies, for example, which turned out to be a bit too
much naive. And so I would say that like in order to bootstrap and grow this kind of credit space,
we need to start with more solid corporation and institution at the beginning, just to make sure
that DeFi still get a good reputation on credit side. Then it really depends on the kind of deployment,
for example, we work a lot with Maven 11 credit as a curator for file connects. And what they do is
pretty much on the underwriting side of things for the credit line that we have, there's been a
lot of work around the covenants that are around the credit line. So the borrower has a certain
kind of parameters and action that they can do. And at the moment, Maven 11 is monitoring that.
And we're doing the same for other borrowers like Fazanara or Boston trading, for example.
So it takes an initial screen of the wealthiness and the and creditworthiness of the borrowers,
and then it takes also monitoring tools and monitoring capabilities for making sure that
the alphiness of the borrower is still there. It's a bit manual at the moment, but I will
like goal in the next, I would say, year is to automate that process. And actually,
just to introduce a bit, a new concept here. But what we see as a really interesting
implementation into this kind of credit line is zero knowledge technology. Because what we
realized is that most of the information and data that we need to monitor and review to make
sure that there is a good creditworthiness for a borrower are sensible data for the borrower.
The borrower doesn't feel really comfortable in making this kind of information completely public,
both for compliance reason, but also for like just to be ahead of other competitors and not to
fall behind other competitors. And what we saw is that like ZK technology really fits well
in this kind of area of monitoring, creating warnings and covenants for certain credit lines.
So I'll give you a really really simple example of that. Let's say that a credit line for an
institutional borrower has a covenant that says that the borrower can only deploy files into
tier one exchanges, and no more than 25% of the entire loan amount can be deployed into a single
exchange. So the borrower doesn't want to expose all this kind of data for all the reason that they
have. And by using ZK technology and more precisely ZK TLS, we essentially encrypt these kind of data.
And what the lenders receive is a proof of the fact that the covenant is respected,
and so also that the creditworthiness of the borrower is still there. And in this way, we also
to make the process from a more traditional monthly reporting or like a certificate of collateral
on a specific custodian that is issued, then you need to completely rely on a single data source.
Two, the idea is to have the borrower being able to plug in multiple data sources from centralized
exchanges, custodian accounts, bank accounts, even encrypt this kind of data. So all the
sensible information are protected, and it's privacy preserving for your final borrower.
But the lenders on the other side are able to get a proof of the fact that the
exponents are respected, and the borrower creditworthiness is still good.
Is there some sort of second opinion for the underwriting? So kind of, do you have different
companies kind of look at the same loans, or is the underwriting in some way incentivized or penalized?
Do they kind of make a wrong assessment? I mean, wrong assessment, it goes a long way here,
right? Because kind of like everyone acknowledges from the get-go that there is some level of risk,
and kind of in order to kind of say whether something was calculated correctly or not,
kind of you would actually have to run this experiment many times, and kind of like you're
only running it once. So kind of, even if kind of like there's only a 2% chance of default
that is acknowledged, kind of like those 2% can materialize, right? So kind of how do you
do quality assurance on the underwriters? That's a good question, because we have been thinking
about this, because of course, like underwriting process is not like a mathematically something
that mathematically you can you can always like be right. So of course, overall, we could expect
the folds in the as we scale up this kind of credit protocol. So we can all like say, okay,
there won't be any defaults. So we need to build around mitigating also this kind of default risk.
And one way at the moment, essentially, each credit line can be curated by a single curator.
So there's a one entity that takes care of on the writing and monitoring the alphonies of the
borrower. But the guardrail and the essentially the protection that we embedded into it is that
the curator is also a legal representative for the lenders. So it doesn't take care only
on the under of the underwriting process and monitoring process for the borrower. But in a case
of a default, the curator in this case is becomes the lender represent legal representative towards
the borrower. So the incentive, of course, for the curator is to make sure that they are doing
the right calculation in order to get the default risk and also to make sure that they didn't they
don't underestimate this kind of default risk, because then they are responsible for any legal
representation for the lenders, which is actually another difference from other protocols. Other
protocols, essentially, if you're a lender and it happens to be a default, it's up to you to go to
court to to file the bankruptcy, for example, documents in order to get back in usually multiple
years, any proceed from the liquidation of the borrowers. Instead, in the setup that we have
is the curator that is also taking care of this process. So of course, because of that, the curator
is more incentivized to do a proper due diligence and proper monitoring of the borrower. Even if it
means to be more conservative than than the usual process, but that's the initial incentive. Of course,
there's not a final setup, I would say, over time, for example, yeah, having multiple creators
with kind of different roles, like one on the right in initially doing due diligence, another
one doing monitoring just to have like multiple parties that provides an understanding of the
borrowers makes completely sense. But yeah, at the current time, that would be the incentive for
the curator to provide a proper due diligence and provide a proper underwriting process.
What happens if the underwriter just doesn't do it then? So kind of like, say the borrower
defaulted in kind of like there are 20 lenders that kind of now I as an underwriter meant to
represent it. I just don't do it. And I kind of just kind of step out of my business and let it
default, start up a new underwriting business and kind of start from square one until because
kind of defaults are kind of if you if you play it in any way kind of correctly, defaults are rare,
right? Kind of like default should be rare. So if I kind of if I can run my business
until the first default unfettered, is isn't, am I not incentivized to do that?
Yeah, I see I see what you're saying, but actually there would be liabilities for the
underwriters as well. So of course, I see what you're saying that you just like close out the
underwriting business on that entity and you open up a new one, but you completely destroy the
reputation of your underwriting process. So these are known entities, you know, who they are and
kind of like there's kind of like a soft reputation, even if it's not on chain kind of, you know,
I would say, yeah, institutional, like in general, on chain credit is big given we work with a spectrum
of collateral, because we could we can enable borrowers putting collateral, of course, but we
can work with a full spectrum of collateral from kind of standard collateralization ratio to even
zero collateral. I think it's all about reputation, like all these kinds of lending is also reputation
based lending. So okay, I see a lot of also borrowers institutional borrowers at the moment
that are looking at this kind of under collateralized credit lines as a way to to build a credit score
that is like it's it's on chain and all the interest payments that they make, all the
repayments of the notion that they make is essentially something that builds a credit score that is
on chain and it's immutable on chain. So I would say that one like a big part of the of managing
these kind of credit lines is also making sure that the borrower but also the underwriters has
this kind of reputation based way of working on the credit lines. Okay, so I think we kind of cover
the how and the why and kind of the what maybe let's let's look at the house. So kind of like
if you if if you could walk me through the mechanics kind of like from the lenders deposit to kind of
how the credit gets allocated and how the year is paid out and how often kind of these loans are
novated and so on. I think kind of that that would that would go a long way.
No, yeah, absolutely. So what the process of lending out to to a specific credit line
we are from a UX perspective. I would say we made sure to make it as as much similar to the
normal DeFi UX as possible. So initial like you know, liquidity providers could feel it. They were
still like in DeFi. Of course, there are some compliance requirements that we need to respect
depending on the jurisdiction of the borrower. So all the credit lines at the moment have a KYC
process that you need to go through as a lender before being able to deposit. And so after that,
like you can of course you can access all the data around the borrower or all the data around
the performance of the vault and make sure that these respect the risk reward profile that you want
app for your for your credit exposure. The kind of like the duration and the interest rate models
of the credit lines that really depends on the borrowers because as I mentioned before, we built
the protocol around customizability and modularity of the credit lines. So the borrower can really
decide how the interest rate model behaves and what is the duration or the covenants of the of
the credit line. So just to give you some example just to let also the audience here understand
better understand how the current credit lines works. We do have usually like weekly to monthly
duration of these kind of credit lines. At the end of which the borrower needs to pay the interest
rate, the lenders can request withdrawals and borrowers have like different duration from weekly
to monthly to satisfy this kind of withdrawal request. And so the interest rate model for example,
it's decided be with the underwriter, but also the borrower. So for example, Fazanara,
which is one of the borrowers that we have wanted to have a flexible on-shin credit line
that we done interest rate that was based on an external benchmark. So Fazanara digital is
currently running a built delta neutral strategy doing a funding rate arbitrage strategy. And so
they wanted to have the on-shin credit line attached to the performance of these kind of
funding rate strategy. So we took up a benchmark which is the open interest rate at the BTC funding
rate times 1.3, which turned out to be 88% correlated to Fazanara performance. And so we integrated
this kind of interest rate model into the into the credit line. So that's how we can like the
customizability is really it's something that can be used within credit lines and really changes
the way the credit lines work. For example, instead with Falcon X is pretty much traditional. It's a
fixed rate facility with 30 days callback period. So it mimics a bit more the traditional kind of
credit lines that they already had. But with the advantage of now, for example, Falcon X credit
line is being used as a collateral in Marfo. So lenders can also perform looping strategies
on Marfo or even just, you know, use it as a collateral tomorrow out to USDC and deploy USDC
somewhere else. So you bring also more capital efficiency. So the process of deploying funds
is pretty similar to DeFi standard, I would say UX apart from the KYC process. Different
story also for USP and SUSP, which is the yield being stable kind that we we put on top of that.
But I'm gonna stop here and not sure if you have other questions on the on the credit lines himself.
Yes, you said there is compile 3 KYC. Is that just for the lender or just for the borrower or
also for the lender? Also for the lender, yeah. And what are the requirements on the lender here?
It depends on the borrower in the sense that different jurisdictions are required different
level of KYC. For example, Falcon X hits US based and we do let's say traditional KYC process. So
getting all the documentation source of funds, corporate documentation, if it's an entity that
is deploying funds into Falcon X. And so I would say it's more traditional kind of KYC process.
We introduced those in partnership with our KYC provider, which is Keering. The proof of KYC
way for some of the some of the borrowers are fine with it. And essentially what we do is letting
the user login into our application via Coinbase, Binance, OKX accounts. And these allows us to
hinder it the KYC level that they have on those centralized exchanges. So user doesn't have to
redo again all the KYC process with this kind of KYC process that we have. But they just need to
login with Coinbase, Binance, OKX, or even we do have Raveloot, for example, as a possibility to
login with. And we hinder it and we get a sort of proof of KYC. And that's for some jurisdiction
enough for the borrower to be respecting the compliance requirement that they have. So those
are the two current ways that we can allow lenders to KYC. And depends on the credit lines and the
jurisdiction of the borrower. And are the timelines for borrowers and vendors typically
different? So kind of like my naive assumption would be that as a borrower, kind of I prefer
longer timelines, whereas as a lender, I want to be able to kind of recall my loan kind of like
from week to week. Do you see this in practice? Yeah, we definitely do see that in practice.
I would say it's pretty much a process of finding kind of a credit market equilibrium in the sense
that we do receive requests from borrowers to have longer duration of these kinds of loans. And on
the other side, lenders ask for shorter durations in order to be able to recall funds. What we saw is
that using a marketplace approach to that. So the borrower can propose different duration and let
the lenders feel the credit line that they prefer to have makes sense. Of course, like the behavior
that we see is that usually borrowers prefer to have longer duration. But for longer duration,
they know that they have to increase the interest rate. So it's kind of like having the borrowers
bidding and providing these different terms to the lenders. And then the lenders find an
equilibrium and find a sort of like natural deployment into the volts that they respect. That
they respect the risk reward profile and also the duration that they want. So there is kind of a
process of finding the equilibrium at the beginning where the borrower proposed different duration
and different interest rate models. And the lenders pick and choose the one that they prefer. And
yeah, having this kind of like marketplace approach allows this allows us to have like multiple
proposals from a borrower. Lenders decide which one is better for them and naturally than the
borrowers keep the one with more liquidity into that it that is being allocated into it.
Okay, you also kind of briefly touched upon this earlier, but kind of there's also this synthetic
dollar product that you have. Walk us through that. Yeah, so we decided to introduce this kind of
synthetic yield bearing asset into built on top of the credit lines. Because well, on one side,
we wanted to create a sort of like index of these kind of credit lines. What we observed is that
some institutional allocators wants to control their credit exposure. So they want to create
their own credit allocation. And so they pick and choose different credit lines with different
allocations. And that's their own decision. But some other like institutional allocators actually
wants to have exposure to pretty much a diversified basket of credit lines. And they don't want to
really like trigger and control all and and monitor all the exposure that they have. They're just fine
with all the borrowers and they want to have exposure to all the borrowers. And so on one side,
USP and SUSP, which is the name of the synthetic dollar and yield bearing synthetic dollar that we
have allows to have a basket of assets to access a basket of credit lines instead of having to
pick and choose all the credit lines. And on the other side, actually these create some way for
less sophisticated investors to access these kind of credit exposure. You can see that as a sort of
like ETFs compared to be can choose stocks and build your own stocks portfolio. And so the way
that that USP and SUSP works is that you deposit USDC or in the future USDT and USDS for example.
And these table currents get allocated across a basket of credit lines, which currently we
proposed an initial allocation mechanism, which is kind of the generating rules of the expertise
that would build with idle finance and the yield aggregation with idle finance. But in this way,
in these instances, it takes the borrower creditworthiness, the duration of the loan,
the interest rate model, it creates a diversified allocation across these kinds of borrowers. And
also always keeps a reserve that is highly liquid to being able to meet the withdrawal
request from this table coin. And so these gives access also to a less sophisticated,
but also to a, I would say a permissionless kind of audience because having this kind of
synthetic dollar and yield bearing, synthetic dollar allows us to apply the let's call it
circle model. You know, if you want to have you as DC a mint or redeem you as DC, you need to
be KYC, do you need to go through circle onboarding process and then you're able to mint and redeem
USDC against dollars. But you can actually acquire or sell USDC on secondary markets,
on taxes, for example. And this is something that we can apply as well to USP and SUSP.
So permissionless user that doesn't want to go through KYC, they can acquire USP,
in Uniswap curve balancer, for example, stick it and then eventually sell it back into Uniswap
balancer or curve. So this allows also to broaden the audience and the access to this kind of
crediting next also to a permissionless kind of audience and not only to a permissioned
kind of audience. I have several follow ups here. So the first one being kind of like a mechanical
one. So seeing that I can kind of deposit into this pool anytime, kind of how do you make sure
that the size of the pool is commensurate with kind of the borrow volume that you see.
You're saying that since you can deposit into USP whenever you want, how do we match that with
borrowing requests on the other side? That's a really good question. At the current scale of
USP and SUSP, that's not being an issue. So we have more borrow demand.
Exactly. We do have more borrowing demand at the moment, but it's an aspect that we have been
thinking about. And I think that what fits by well is that we can also integrate blue, cheap,
DeFi yield sources as a way to park this kind of capital if there is not enough borrowing demand.
Like for example, deploying into SUSDS, the old DSR from MakerDAU or into AvaUSDC Ethereum pool,
which are kind of blue cheap. Exactly. Okay, second question,
kind of previously kind of in terms of legal defensibility. So kind of previously, I can see
how you say, okay, we're just kind of the matchmaker here, kind of like this is a one-to-one
relationship. But kind of like with USP, arguably, you're offering kind of an investment product,
right? Are you worried about that? So how the legal clarity around that still to be shaped, I
would say, but yeah, we are thinking around that. We don't want to completely be an investment
advisor, I would say, on this kind of thing. Because of course, yeah, like we deal with aggregators,
if there is a central team, a central entity that just proposed their locations,
you end up to be an investment advisor. And that's kind of borrowing a concept from what we build
also with Adul Finance, which is that we, the allocation mechanism for the USDC or USDT or
USDS that we that are backing USP, it's open. So essentially, Pareto, we don't have the token
live right now, it's going to be, it's going to be released because the governance process of
Aareto Dow, in this case, would be able to also elect, create a locator manager. So we're not going
to be the only one proposing a location, but there would be an idealistically speaking
and net work. Your market plays again for different investment strategies. Exactly, exactly. Okay, so
maybe I checked this morning and didn't seem terribly liquid, right? So kind of, what's going
on there? So kind of like, what's the what's the rate of return you currently offering,
and why is it not attractive enough for users? I would say, so we currently have around
four million, four or five million into into USP. I think it's still taking a bit of time to
bootstrap the liquidity over there because what we are missing in our opinion is the
additional use cases with integrations with like over collateralized protocols or pandals.
So I would say that currently the interest rate on USP is around 11, 12%. And it's really like
depending on the borrowers that we have currently, we do have like three borrowers integrated within
USP and we need to expand that in order to make sure that we can, on one side, diversify the
exposure more for this kind of index, but also being able to allocate to higher yields in order
to become more attractive in general for the market. I would say that the major problem that we found
out is to bootstrap the integrations, so being able to use as USP as a collateral in more for
Euler or Ava, for example, create a more liquid fixed rate facility. So, for example, in Pando,
being able to have this kind of fixed rate. And of course, I mean, we're still early in the
development of SUSP and I think we can make more, you know, we can push it more on the visibility
side of things, which is something that we haven't done a lot yet, but because we wanted to have
all the infrastructure ready and test it out and battle test it, I would say. So, I would say,
it's not really about the interest rate, because if you look at, I would say, Athena, for example,
what is right now, Athena should be around like five, six percent, if I remember correctly,
they are overly allocated also to like USDS, so it should be quite similar to the SSR rate.
So, it should be around that. So, we're kind of like, we're giving double of the interest rate
of that. So, I don't see the interest rate as a major problem. I see more like being able to
integrate the USP and SUSP across other protocols, which is something that we're doing. We started
with Euler a couple of weeks ago and bootstrapping that. We're gonna push it more for getting things
listed as collateral as it's a pain. Yeah, it is, but I mean, it makes sense, so it should be kind
of like a... It should be a pain, but... Exactly, exactly. Otherwise, it's hiring the risk for
defines, I don't know. But it was like pushing on visibility and dedication, it's something that
we're gonna do in the next month, which would be helpful to understand what is USP, what is SSP,
where the yield is coming from, and these we expect will bring also more liquidity and more
scale up scale to the USP and SUSP. Okay, credit in some sense is more opaque
than most DeFi activity, right? Because it heavily depends on off-chain books that you don't
necessarily have access to as a user. How do you make this compatible, or do you make this compatible,
with the real-time transparency that people expect from DeFi? That's a great point. So currently,
it's difficult to make this kind of process really comparable to the real-time automation
monitoring of DeFi, but we need to go there. We need to improve from traditional loan that often
rely on quarterly, monthly reports, to verify barwell health. And these creates also a risk
lag, because you might find out too late that a covenant was breached, for example.
So yeah, like ZKTLS, implementing ZKTLS would be the first step towards that, towards a more
automated monitoring process, and also being able to have a diversified access to different data
sources from the borrower allows us to verify from multiple data sources that the borrower
else is there, compared to just a single data source, or a single audit or that makes the
auditing process on the borrower. So I would say that one of the current implementation that we
have in mind to solve this is to create this kind of ZKTLS model, where the borrower can
attach multiple data sources with different even frequency of data, but to try to be as close to
the real-time monitoring process that we have in DeFi. And so monitoring and automating this
process for the borrower, so they don't have to provide manual reports and monthly or quarterly
reports. It's kind of a step towards going close to the real-time monitoring that we have in DeFi.
Yeah, so my worry is primarily about malicious behavior. So I do agree that kind of all kinds of
unfortunate business consequences and so on. I think kind of like this is where I could buy this.
I'm not a finance person, but kind of I know that kind of like if I needed to kind of make
books look good, depending on kind of like I would book things different ways or kind of like I
would delay the booking. I think there's different ways of kind of fudging the books, right? So that
kind of crisis is not immediately apparent. Do you have any guardrails against truly malicious
borrower behavior? Yeah, I would say not relying solely on proprietary data sources. So I would say
like getting financial statements, bank records, the trading activities in general to form this kind
of borrower reputation shouldn't be something that a borrower itself is providing. But it's
something that we fetch from the data sources that are third parties. And for example, it's a
read-only API from a checks account. So the borrower itself cannot really like
manipulate this kind of data. It would be checks that should be manipulate. Of course,
there is an assumption of trust. But they can open a second account, right? So kind of like I
can have one clean finance account and open a second account in the same name, right?
Yeah, but when you're opening this kind of credit line, you're attaching like the either like
like all the funds that you are borrowing out from the credit line should be verified that goes to
that specific checks account. And all the activity around that checks account is what we are monitoring.
So the collateral that you're using, the kind of trading activity that you're doing from that
account is what matters for the lender. So I would say these kind of like credit lines should be
getting a mix between other accounts, but should be related to a specific checks account
from the borrower side. And in general, like the way that we are also structuring from a,
I would say legal perspective, the credit lines is that they are SPV based. So there are also
some bankruptcy remotes from the, let's say, main company as well. Okay. So that that's
trying to ring fans as much as possible. Exactly. So if the Pareto interface and kind of like the
centralized entities behind it kind of disappeared this afternoon, could I still unwind my loan or
redeem my USP just by interacting with smart contracts? Or do I kind of rely on you guys to
kind of provide this service to me? No, it would be possible. The way that we made the protocol
itself, especially on USP and SPS side is that there can be a way for the DAO itself to change,
for example, the admin controls for the allocation mechanism, for example, that also allows to,
let's say we call back all the borrowers, all the funds from the borrowers and repay all the
USP token holders. So if we call it, we have been calling it in this kind of test with our legal
advisor, the Bahamas test. So if all the team decide to go to Bahamas and just don't be able
the protocol anymore, we need to have a way to let the community and the token holders to be able to
change the parameters and to change the admin controls, recall all the loans and repay back
USP and SPS. So yeah, we have been thinking about that. And since the beginning, the protocol is
made to be open in a way that it doesn't only rely on the core team.
Maybe as a closing question, if you look at the on-chain private credit market and
Pareto in particular, what does success for you guys look like in the next two to three years?
Nice, great question in the sense that of course, the main metric that we're using in DeFi is
TVL. So that's kind of a North Star for all the DeFi projects. And that's what we need to,
what we're focused on growing over time. And that comes, of course, from creating a more and more
diversified market marketplace. So what I see as a growth driver and potential expansion for Pareto
in the next two, three years, I would say, is to gradually introduce non-crypto-related
borrowers. We want to have a way to give away those two lenders and equity providers in general,
to not rely only on borrowers that are related to the crypto market, because then depending on the
market cycle, you're completely subject to the market cycle. And so the first driver would be
to expand into more corporate bonds, corporate loans kind of credit lines. So introducing kind
of like FinTech companies or cross-border payment facilities, credit card companies,
account receivable companies, still related to finance and FinTech, but that would be the first
expansion. And so creating this kind of more and more diversified marketplace that would allow
us to grow USP and SUSP diversification power, and allow us to work with a larger basket of
borrowers, borrowers' capabilities and loans in general, to grow to grow USP and SUSP. So I would
say two, three years, we are more new kind of corporate borrowers. We are more new curators
that in our vision are also like traditional institutions that bring their own underwriting
process and due diligence process on shame without having to build everything from scratch.
And of course that would be like meaning a TVL that goes above 1 billion to like numbers that
were more like, you know, credit market is a 15 trillion market all around the world. So we do
have a lot of room of expansion here in DeFi. So like our first like milestone is 1 billion
of TVL, but then we need to think bigger with like this kind of number and we need to grow from there.
Cool. Mateo, where do we send people to find out more about Pareto and kind of potentially
borrow or lend some money with you guys? I would say let's definitely direct users and the audience
that is interested to learn more about Pareto, to Pareto.credit. That would be the main point of
access where you can access the dashboard. So you can see all the both read about the borrowers
that we have read about the strategies that they're running and understand more also about USP
and SUSP. And then I would say if they want to also keep up with the announcement that we make,
which lately are a lot actually to follow us on Twitter @Pareto.credit. You can find all the
links at @Pareto.credit for Twitter as well to look at all the announcements that we're making
and also to read the blog posts and the articles that we made with our partners.
Perfect. Thank you so much for coming on Mateo. It's been a pleasure chatting with you.
Thank you. Likewise.